Guide to the De Forest Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
De Forest family papers
1813-1953
YCAL MSS 582
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.75
(10 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, personal papers, legal and financial records, and related papers of the De Forest family. There is also some correspondence relating to the Sergeant and Shepard families (who married into the De Forest family). Family members prominent in the papers include John Hancock De Forest, his wife Dotha Woodward, and their sons George Frederick De Forest, Henry Alfred De Forest, Andrew Woodward De Forest, and John William De Forest. The papers contain documents relating to John Hancock De Forest's company Humphreysville Manufacturing Company, based in Seymour, Connecticut. Drafts and publications by author John William De Forest, are also part of the papers. Tuberculosis, a book by John William De Forest's son, Louis Shepard De Forest, is also included in the papers.
De Forest family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis Effingham De Forest (Yale 1912), 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm.
Associated Materials
De Forest Family Papers (MS 177). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Sergeant Family Papers (MS 806). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
De Forest Family
The De Forest family was a prominent New England family largely based in Connecticut. John Hancock De Forest owned the Humphreysville Manufacturing Company, a cotton textile mill, in Humphreysville (now Seymour), Connecticut. John Hancock De Forest and Dotha Woodward had four sons: George Frederick De Forest, who managed the Humphreysville Manufacturing Company following his father's death; Henry Alfred De Forest, a medical missionary and graduate of Yale University (B.A., 1832 and M.D., 1835); Andrew Woodward De Forest, a lumber businessman in New Haven; and John William De Forest, an author.
John William De Forest wrote essays, poetry, short stories, and novels (including Miss Ravenel's Conversion from Secession to Loyalty ). De Forest's article "The Great American Novel," published in The Nation, is believed to be the first use of the expression.
The De Forest family has a number of connections with Yale University. Various De Forest family members are graduates of Yale and some established awards. David Curtis De Forest established the De Forest Fund and the De Forest Prize in English Oration at Yale College in 1823. John De Forest (B.A., 1826) established the De Forest Mathematical Prize in 1855 to recognize his son Erastus Lyman De Forest (B.A., 1854).
De Forest Family Tree
Family members who are prominent in the papers appear in boldface.
Benjamin De Forest (1749-1784) m. Mehitabel Curtis Lockwood (1751-1830)
-- 2 David Curtis De Forest (1774-1825) m. Julia Wooster (b. 1796)
--- 3 Carlos Maria De Forest (1813-) m. Margaret Watkins
-- 2 Benjamin DeForest (1780-1848) m. Alma Southmayd
-- 2 Ezra DeForest (1782-1868) m. Laura Wooster
-- 2 John Hancock De Forest (1776-1839) m. Dotha Woodward (d. 1847)
-- 3 George Frederick De Forest (1812-1883) m. Caroline Elizabeth Sergeant (b. 1822); Anna Williams Sergeant (b. 1838)
--- 4 Katharine De Forest
--- 4 Clara De Forest m. David James Burrell
--- 4 George Elliott De Forest m. Adeline Whiting Dix
--- 4 Robert De Forest
-- 3 Henry Alfred De Forest (1814-1858) m. Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant (1817-1896)
-- 3 Andrew Woodward De Forest (1817-1900) m. Lucretia Sturges Bennett (1820-1907)
--- 4 Eugene De Forest (1855-1929) m. Minnie Richards
--- 4 Charles Sturges De Forest (1853-1933) m. Lillian Ives
--- 4 Mary De Forest m. Duncan Leverich
--- 4 Edward m. Louise E. Hawley
--- 4 Lucia H. De Forest (1858-1886)
-- 3 John William De Forest (1826-1906) m. Harriet Silliman Shepard (1833-1878)
---- 4 Louis Shepard De Forest (1857-1938) m. Annie C. Everit (d. 1932)
----- 5 Charles Shepard De Forest
----- 5 Louis Effingham De Forest
Sergeant Family Tree
Sewall Sergeant (1789-1858) m. Clarissa Partridge (1793-1860)
-- 2 Catharine Sedgwick Sergeant (1817-1896) m. Henry Alfred De Forest (1814-1858)
-- 2 George Sergeant (1820-1875) m. Lydia A. Clark (d. 1863)
-- 2 Caroline Elizabeth Sergeant (b. 1822) m. George Frederick De Forest (1812-1883)
-- 2 Susan Sergeant (1825-1827)
-- 2 Sewall Sergeant (1827-1890) m. Alma Mercein
-- 2 Clarissa Partridge Sergeant (1829-1846)
-- 2 Susan Emily Sergeant (b. 1832) m. Alfred H. Dashiell
-- 2 John Elliott Sergeant (1835-1895) m. Caroline H. Matthews
-- 2 Anna Williams (b. 1838) m. George Frederick De Forest(1812-1883)
Shepard Family Tree
Charles Upham Shepard (1804-1886) m. Harriet Taylor
-- 2 Harriett Silliman Shepard (1833-1878) m. John William De Forest(1826-1906)
-- 2 Fanny Shepard m. Charles Pickney James
-- 2 Charles Upham Shepard, Junior
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, personal papers, legal and financial records, and related papers of the De Forest family. There is also some correspondence relating to the Sergeant and Shepard families (who married into the De Forest family). Family members prominent in the papers include John Hancock De Forest, his wife Dotha Woodward, and their sons George Frederick De Forest, Henry Alfred De Forest, Andrew Woodward De Forest, and John William De Forest. John Hancock De Forest's brothers, Benjamin and Ezra De Forest, and their children are also represented in the papers.
Drafts and printed material by and relating to John William De Forest provide insight into his writing career. De Forest's career is similarly reflected in contracts and correspondence with publishers. The Writings series also includes his son Louis Shepard De Forest's book Tuberculosis as a local and contagious disease in New Haven (1891).
Family papers contain business and genealogy documents. Warranty deeds, wills, and estate documents trace the De Forest's wealth and connection to Connecticut history. A number of warranty deeds reflect the De Forest's acquisition of property in Seymour, Derby, and New Haven, Connecticut. Some legal and financial records relate to John Hancock De Forest's company, the Humphreysville Manufacturing Company, and Seymour (formerly Humphreysville), Connecticut. An inventory of Dotha Woodward De Forest's estate following her death lists the contents of the De Forest's home, such as furniture, books, clothing, and other household effects, which combined provide insight into the life of a Connecticut family in the mid-nineteenth century. Military papers and a passport for John William De Forest document his experience as a soldier. The Family Papers series also includes documents pertaining to the histories of the De Forest, Sergeant, and Shepard families.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1813-1953. II. Writings, 1855-1871. III. Family Papers, 1839-1933.
American literature -- 19th century; Connecticut -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Seymour (Conn.) -- History -- 19th century; De Forest, Andrew Woodward, 1817-1900; De Forest, Dotha Woodward, d. 1847; De Forest family; De Forest, George Frederick, 1812-1883; De Forest, Henry Alfred, 1814-1858; De Forest, John Hancock, 1776-1839; De Forest, John William, 1826-1906; De Forest, Louis Effingham, 1891-; De Forest, Louis Shepard, 1857-1938; Sergeant family; Shepard family; Humphreysville Manufacturing Company
- Correspondence, 1813-1953; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents the De Forest family, in addition to families related to the De Forests by marriage including the Sergeant and Shepard families, dating from 1813 to 1953. The correspondence largely reflects the familial bonds between various generations of the De Forest family. John William De Forest's correspondence with publishers reflects his writing career. Third party correspondence with Louis Effingham De Forest pertains to his work preserving the De Forest family history.
  Charles Upham Shepard, a mineralogist, corresponded with a number of prominent figures, including Charles Darwin and Ralph Waldo Emerson.
  - De Forest, Andrew Woodward
    - Letter to David James Burrel, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters to George Frederick De Forest, 1825-1836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters to John Hancock and Dotha Woodward De Forest, 1827-1836 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter from George W. Edwards, 1838 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Charles Cutler Prince, 1833-1845 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - De Forest, Benjamin
    - Letters to Andrew Woodward De Forest (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letter to John Hancock De Forest, 1826 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - De Forest, Carlos Maria, letters to various family members, 1826-1837 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - De Forest, Caroline Sergeant, letters to various family members, 1844-1862 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    12 letters to family members including 7 letters to her brother George Sergeant, 3 to Susan Sergeant Dasheil, 1 to her sister Katherine Sergeant De Forest, and 1 to her mother Clarissa Sergeant
  - De Forest, Dotha Woodward
    - Letters to George, Henry and Andrew De Forest, 1823-1839 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Sarah Woodward Smith, 1826-1835 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters from Elijah Woodward, 1827-1828 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - De Forest, Ezra, letters to John Hancock De Forest, 1826-1828 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - De Forest, George Elliott, letters to Marjorie Ryan, 1953 July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - De Forest, George Frederick
    - Letters to Andrew Woodward De Forest, 1833-1865 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letters to John Hancock and Dotha Woodward De Forest, 1825-1829 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letter to Henry De Forest, 1823 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter to Caroline Elizabeth Sergeant De Forest, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter from Noah Porter, 1842 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - De Forest, Harriet Silliman Shepard, letters to Andrew De Forest, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - De Forest, Henry Alfred
    - Letters to Andrew Woodward De Forest, 1834-1839 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      11 letters
    - Letters to George Frederick De Forest and George Sergeant, 1832-1837 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letters to John Hancock De Forest, 1835-1836 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letters to John Hancock and Dotha Woodward De Forest, 1825-1835 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Letters to John William De Forest, 1835-1837 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - De Forest, John, letters to John Hancock De Forest, 1826-1827 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    3 letters to his uncle
  - De Forest, John Hancock
    - Letters to Andrew De Forest, 1829-1839 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Letters to Dotha Woodward De Forest, 1813-1829 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Letters to George and Henry De Forest, 1823-1839 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Letters from W. M. Stebbins, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Letters from miscellaneous senders, 1826-1827 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - De Forest, John William
    - Letter to Mr. Buckingham, 1891 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Letters to Caroline Sergeant De Forest, 1851-1855 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Letters to Dotha Woodward De Forest, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Letters to George Frederick De Forest, 1846-1852 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Postcards to Harriet Silliman Shepard De Forest, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letters to Louis and Eugene De Forest, 1888-1901 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Letters to Lucretia De Forest, 1848-1853 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Letters to Harpers, 1865-1887 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Letters from William Dean Howells, 1878-1902 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Letters to Putnam and Underwood, 1859-1886 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Letters to miscellaneous recipients, 1828-1878 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Travel letters, 1846-1855 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Letters from publishers, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Letters from miscellaneous senders, 1829-1901 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - De Forest, Catherine Sergeant, letters to George Sergeant and parents, 1841-1848 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - De Forest, Louis Effingham
    - Correspondence with researchers (including Anne Carabillo Jenovese), 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Correspondence with Eugene Saxton, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Elliot, Charles Wyllys, letter to "My Lady", undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Sergeant, Abigail, letter to Dr. Thomas William, 1751 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Sergeant, Clarissa Partridge
    - Letter to Catherine Sergeant De Forest, 1846 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Letters to Mrs. Starr, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Shepard, Charles Upham
    - Letters to Benjamin Silliman, 1843-1882 (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
    - Letters from miscellaneous senders, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Including J. H. Braddly, Charles Darwin, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Edward Hitchcock, Justus von Liebig, Leonard Lyell, R. C. Gilchrist, John Ruskin, William Graham Sumner, and 1 unidentified
  - Shepard, Mase, 1877 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Writings, 1855-1871, undated; Series II; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Writings by and about John William De Forest and Other Writings.
  The series is largely comprised of documents reflecting John William De Forest's writing career, ranging from drafts to printed versions. In addition the series includes writings about John William De Forest.
  The series also includes Tuberculosis written by John William De Forest's son, Louis Shepard De Forest, who was a medical doctor.
  - Writings by and about John William De Forest
    - "Agnes' Dream," autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - The Bureau Major, autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 61-63)
    - "The Cradle of the Human Race," printed version, The Atlantic Monthly, 1878 February (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "The Enchanted Voyage," original autograph manuscript draft, part four of The Downing Legends, before 1901 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "For Hattie Silman Shepard's Commonplace Book of Poetry," autograph manuscript draft, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Jesse De Forest: Founder of New York, autograph manuscript draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Kate Beaumont, typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, before 1872 (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
    - "Marcus and Hildegarde," typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Miss Ravenel's Conversion from Secession to Loyalty, typescript, before 1867 (Box 4, Folder 71-75)
    - Poems: Medley and Palestina, typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, before 1902 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Overland, printed version with corrections, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Playing the Mischief, autograph manuscript draft, before 1875 (Box 5, Folder 78-79)
    - "Poem," original autograph manuscript draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - A Volunteer's Adventures
      - Autograph manuscript draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 81-83)
      - Typescript with corrections, undated (Box 6, Folder 84-85)
    - Clippings of stories and articles by John William De Forest, undated (Box 7, Folder 86-87)
      "Lieutenant Barker's Ghost Story"; "Parole D'Honneur"; "A Gentleman of the Old School"; "Was it a Ghost"; "My Life on the Plains"; "The Colored Member"; "Captain Horsfall's Romance"; "The Baby Exterminator"; "Captain Phil Glover as President"; "A Case of Vitrification"; "Ancient and Modern Cats" (1874); "Modern Cats" (1874); "Old John Raddle"; "Fate Ferguston"; "An Inspired Lobbyist"; "The Story of a Handkerchief"; "The City of Brass" (1869); "Yesebel"; "Rum Creeters is Women"; "The Drummer Ghost" (1869); "Chanet"; "The Duchesne Estate"; "Father Higgin's Preferment"; "Love in Mount Lebanon"; "The Lauson Tragedy"; "The Isle of the Puritans"; "Mrs. Pullet's Perversions"; "Mr Pullet's Mistake"; The Taillefer Bell-Ringings" (1869); "A Strange Arrival"; "A Night at Sea"; "My Neighbor, the Prophet"; "The Oversoul of Manse Roseburgh"; "The Man with a Nose like an Owl"; "A Queen of Society"; "Tom Mallory's Revenge"; "The Hasheesh Eater"; "The Hungry Heart"; "Caesar's Art of War and of Writing"
    - Pamphlets about John William De Forest, 1931, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      "John William De Forest" by David Porter (1951); Union College Bulletin (1931-32)
    - Clipping about John William De Forest, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - "John William De Forest: Realist and Soldier" by Anne Jenovese, unpublished thesis; typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 90-91)
    - "John William De Forest" by James F. Light, original typescript draft, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 92-94)
  - Other Writings
    - Tuberculosis by Louis Shepard De Forest, 1891 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Griffin, George Butler, writing on David Curtis De Forest, undated (Box 8, Folder 96)
- Family Papers, 1839-1933; Series III; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Series III is organized into two subseries: Business Papers and Genealogy Papers.
  The series contains various documents relating to the De Forest family's businesses and personal lives. A number of records pertain to the Humphreysville Manufacturing Company and the De Forest's acquisition of various real estate in Seymour, Connecticut. John Hancock De Forest's will and the inventory of his home with Dotha Woodward De Forest provide insight into the wealth and property of a prominent Connecticut family.
  - Business Papers
    - De Forest, Andrew Woodward, miscellaneous business papers, 1839-1872 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - De Forest, Dotha Woodward, inventory of estate, 1848 January 21 (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - De Forest, George Frederick, articles of agreement, 1844-1854 (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - De Forest, John Hancock
      - Warranty deeds, 1821-1823 (Box 9, Folder 100)
      - Will and estate, 1837-1839 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - De Forest, John William
      - Miscellaneous papers, warranty deed, passport, bills, 1849-1902 (Box 9, Folder 102)
      - Military records, 1864-1897 (Box 9, Folder 103)
      - Contracts with publishers, 1867-1903 (Box 9, Folder 104)
      - Biographical material, 1916-1933 (Box 9, Folder 105)
      - List of periodicals reviewing De Forest's works, undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Genealogy Papers
    - De Forest Family, undated (Box 10, Folder 107-108)
    - Parridge Family, undated (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Sergeant Family, undated (Box 10, Folder 110)